Guide to the Puebla Archives
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Civil Cases, 1567-1878; Series III
  - C. Cayetano Olvero for Luz Lezama vs. Alejo Lezano concerning money, 1868 (Box 44, Folder 1092)
  - Petition concerning the estate and will of Margarita Sánchez, 1869 (Box 44, Folder 1093)
  - Case against Ventura Sánchez for abandoning her home, 1878 (Box 44, Folder 1094)
  - Petition by María Castro concerning sale of her house, undated (Box 44, Folder 1095)
  - Petition by José Manolo Corta that his wife, who has deserted him, be brought to court, undated (Box 44, Folder 1096)
  - Petition by Joachina de Lastra, orphan, denouncing her treatment by Paula Iniges, undated (Box 44, Folder 1097)
  - Petition to the Governor by Juan Pedo Mendoza that he be released from prison, undated (Box 44, Folder 1098)
  - Petition to the Governor by María del Carmen Molina that her daughter María Francisca Barcona be released from prison, undated (Box 44, Folder 1099)
  - Rita Muñoz vs. soldiers for destruction of her meon, undated (Box 44, Folder 1100)
  - Petition to the Governor by Ana Prado, Spaniard, that her husband, José Mariano Carrillo, be released from prison, undated (Box 44, Folder 1101)
  - José Ramirez de Arellano vs. José Antonio Peréz concerning a sum of money, undated (Box 44, Folder 1102)
  - Concerning the case of Juan Ramirez Freile y Arellano and Pedro Gómez Almansa, Undated (1600s) (Box 44, Folder 1103)
  - Petition by María Rosa Ramirez that her son, José María Balentin be released from prison, undated (Box 44, Folder 1104)
  - Appraisal of the Hacienda of Santa María Orocutín, undated (Box 44, Folder 1105)
  - Petition by the orphan son of the late Nicolás de Santia concerning a horse and mare his late father had paid for, undated (Box 44, Folder 1106)
  - Petition to the Governor by Joaquín de Teran that he be released from prison, undated (Box 44, Folder 1107)
  - Petition to the Governor by María Gertrúdis Zoralba concerning a debt owed to her late husband, undated (Box 44, Folder 1108)
  - Petition by María Joséfa Viveros that her son, José Nicolás be released from prison, undated (Box 44, Folder 1109)
- Miscellaneous Records, 1594-1901; Series IV
  - Decree by the King of Spain concerning colonial matters (incomplete), Circa 1594 (Box 44, Folder 1110)
  - Lease of stores belonging to Juan del Barrio to Alonso Ortíz, Circa 1602 (Box 44, Folder 1111)
  - Acknowledgment of debt owed by Alonso Rodríguez to Juan de Olivares, 1606 (Box 44, Folder 1112)
  - Loan of money executed by Pedro de Caravajal to Cristóbal Ferrer, 1610 (Box 44, Folder 1113)
  - Loan of money from Pedro Delgado de Monzon to Andrés Fernández de la Muela and his bondsman, 1615 (Box 44, Folder 1114)
  - Record of earnings of Luisa and Beatriz, negroes, 1619 - 1623 (Box 44, Folder 1115)
  - Deeds, records of houses and blacksmith shop formerly belonging to Gabriel de Torija, and now belonging to the Convent of Sta. Domingo, Zanguitlán, 1621 - 1686 (Box 44, Folder 1116)
  - Certificate of Notarization signed by court scribes, 1646 (Box 44, Folder 1117)
  - Lease of houses belonging to Melchor de Escabar to Simón de Costa, 1647 (Box 44, Folder 1118)
  - Record of the chaplaincy founded by Mateo de la Cruz with 2,000 pesos for the Church of the Sacred Convent of the Sisters of Our Lady of the Conception, 1650 - 1656 (Box 45, Folder 1119)
  - Record of the chaplaincy founded with 2,000 pesos by Juan Rodríguez of San Miguél, 1656 - 1659 (Box 45, Folder 1120)
  - Payment of wages to Miguél de Zauala by Joseph de Valdez, Pedro Rodríguez and José Calvente, 1674 (Box 45, Folder 1121)
  - Record of the chaplaincy founded by Capt. Luis Carrillo y Alarcón, 1675 - 1855 (Box 45, Folder 1122)
  - Joseph Sulgarin Salgado, certificate of rent administration, 1696 - 1700 (Box 45, Folder 1123)
  - Record of the chaplaincy of Fernando Medrano de Riva de Neira from Atlisco, whose rescission and admission was tried for by D. Antonio Medrano priebendary to the Sta. Iglesia de Valladolid, 1699 - 1718 (Box 45, Folder 1124)
  - Proof of legitimacy and purity of lineage of Juana María Nepomuceno Guillén and family, 1702 - 1825 (Box 45, Folder 1125)
  - Water property of San Francisco Chietla, copy of the original deed, 1703 (Box 46, Folder 1126)
  - Deeds and dispatches concerning Cristóbal Santiago Prioste and other citizens of the neighborhood of Nuestra Señora de la Concepción in Puebla, 1708 - 1758 (Box 46, Folder 1127)
  - Proof of purity of lineage of Pedro Sánchez Contero and Juan Sánchez Quiroz, 1711 (Box 46, Folder 1128)
  - Martín de Aranguti del Castillo, investigation of his filiation as legitimate son of Capt. Martín de Aranguti, 1715 (Box 46, Folder 1129)
  - Chaplaincy founded by Gregorio Rodriguez in his will written in Latin, 1727 (Box 46, Folder 1130)
  - Felipe Fernández de Lugo and María Manuela, certificate of marriage, 1728 (Box 46, Folder 1131)
  - Antonio de Luca payment of debts, 1746 - 1749 (Box 46, Folder 1132)
  - Blas Antonio Peréz, free mulatto, and Juana Manuela concerning betrothal, 1747 (Box 46, Folder 1133)
  - Deed of a house belonging to Joseph Ortíz, bought from Miguél Ponse de Leon, 1750 - 1770 (Box 46, Folder 1134)
  - Record of chaplaincy founded with 3,000 pesos by Doña Micaela Gregoria Malpica Delgado, requiring twenty-five masses to be prayed for each year, 1758-1859 (Box 46, Folder 1135)
  - Surrender of the original title of the lands of San Pedro Ahuatlan and Aguatepeque to Juan Mathias, Indian, 1759 (Box 46, Folder 1136)
  - Mexico. Viceroyalty. Provisional instructions for the defense of Veracruz, by José de Galvez, 1767 (Box 46, Folder 1137)
  - Joseph Antonio Olguin and Gertrúdis de Soto, certificate of marriage, 1766 (Box 46, Folder 1138)
  - Mexico. Viceroyalty. Account book of various estates, kept by L. D. Antonio de Lecca, lawyers, 1770 - 1790 (Box 46, Folder 1139)
  - Decree concerning the deplorable state of Puebla, 1774 (Box 46, Folder 1140)
  - Decree by Joseph Merino y Zenallas, governor, concerning itinerant salesmen, 1775 (Box 46, Folder 1141)
  - Records of cattle, 1776 (Box 46, Folder 1142)
  - Carlos Fernández de Lara and Rosa Fernández de San Miguél, accounts and records, 1776 - 1789 (Box 46, Folder 1143)
  - Decree by Gaspar de Portola, governor, concerning proceedings by family following a death, 1777 (Box 46, Folder 1144)
  - Account notebook of Francisco Cruzado, 1776 - 1782 (Box 46, Folder 1145)
  - Decree on education, 1779 (Box 46, Folder 1146)
  - Report to the Viceroy concerning appointment of authorities, 1779 (Box 46, Folder 1147)
  - Letter from the viceroy to the governor of Puebla, to inform him of cases against José Bretón and Juan de Sta. Rosa, 1780 (Box 46, Folder 1148)
  - Francisco de Terraza y Monter concerning a chaplaincy, 1781 (Box 47, Folder 1149)
  - Records of Gaspar de Gomara, administrator of tobacco in Puebla, 1781 - 1790 (Box 47, Folder 1150)
  - Marriage certificate of Francisco Arregui and María Joséfa Laso de la Vega, 1782 (Box 47, Folder 1151)
  - Deed of sale of the Hacienda Quacualoy Ancita, Cholula, to Pedro de Anchia for 22,000 pesos, 1782 - 1791 (Box 47, Folder 1152)
  - Decree by Jacobo Ugartey Loyola, governor, concerning elections, 1784 (Box 47, Folder 1153)
  - Receipt of 1650 pesos from the pulquería of Aguilar, 1784 - 1791 (Box 47, Folder 1154)
  - José Mariano Cavallero de la Vega and María Joséfa de Arebalo concerning marriage, 1785 (Box 47, Folder 1155)
  - Mexico. Viceroyalty. Wine and vinegar, records of earnings under the jurisdiction of Capt. Ignacio de la Pesa, ruler of Mexico City, 1787 - 1789 (Box 47, Folder 1156)
  - Chaplaincy founded by Capt. José Bringas de Mansaneda according to the wishes of the late José Antonio de la Lama, 1788 (Box 47, Folder 1157)
  - Petition by Chicontepec, citizens of, concerning election of authorities, 1789 (Box 47, Folder 1158)
  - Petition by Manuel Alvarez Estrada to marry Joséfa Espinobarros, 1789 (Box 47, Folder 1159)
  - Election of mayors and other authorities of the Indians, 1789 - 1790 (Box 47, Folder 1160)
  - List of debts owned by priests during 1788, 1789 - 1790 (Box 47, Folder 1161)
  - Register of the Royal Storehouse of Tobacco, 1790 (Box 47, Folder 1162)
  - Proceedings of financial report of the delegate to Igualapa, 1790 - 1792 (Box 47, Folder 1163)
  - Proceedings to announce to the public that the lands and rentable haciendas under the jurisdiction of Huayacocotla and Chicontepec will be sold to the highest bidder, 1790 - 1793 (Box 47, Folder 1164)
  - Settling of bills with the Treasurer of Pepeaca concerning taxes from pulque, 1790 - 1815 (Box 47, Folder 1165)
  - Decrees concerning receipt of goods by the executor for Joachim Lasso and record of sale, 1791 - 1795 (Box 47, Folder 1166)
  - Petition to the governor by te citizens of Ustra Sra. Del Rosario de Alducia denouncing the subdelegate, 1792 (Box 47, Folder 1167)
  - Record of judicial expenditures (incomplete), 1792 (Box 47, Folder 1168)
  - Record of expenditures, 1792 (Box 47, Folder 1169)
  - Record of income and expenditures, 1792 (Box 47, Folder 1170)
  - Sale of the house Nicho, belonging to José Espejo, 1793 (Box 47, Folder 1171)
  - Mexico. Viceroyalty. Book 12 of records of rents, etc., in Mexico City kept by Joseph Pascual Covian de los Rios, 1793 - 1794 (Box 47, Folder 1172)
  - Petitions by the citizens of Cholula that they may retain their subdelegate, 1794 (Box 47, Folder 1173)
  - Petition by María Antonia de Ortega Cavallero that she be given proof of the purity of her lineage, 1794 (Box 47, Folder 1174)
  - Petition by Pedro García Huesca that he be relieved of his position, 1796 (Box 47, Folder 1175)
  - Mexico. Viceroyalty. Record of rents. Kept by Joseph Pascual de los Rios, of Mexico City, 1797 (Box 47, Folder 1176)
  - Records of earnings by the local government, 1797 - 1798 (Box 47, Folder 1177)
  - Petition by José Blanco to marry María del Carmen Ortega, 1798 (Box 48, Folder 1178)
  - Reply to request for places granted in the Plaza de la Compania, 1798 (Box 48, Folder 1179)
  - Two fragments of documents, 1798, undated (Box 48, Folder 1180)
  - Mexico. Viceroyalty. Records of pulque, 1798 - 1800 (Box 48, Folder 1181)
  - Petition by some citizens of Chretla concerning their preference that Pedro Antonio de Irrigaray be their subdelegate, 1799 (Box 48, Folder 1182)
  - Decree concerning property of the Royal Chamber, 1799 (Box 48, Folder 1183)
  - Report to the Viceroy by Cipriano Salinero, appointed to deal with a case against the subdelegate of Chietla, 1799 (Box 48, Folder 1184)
  - Isidro de Alarcon, report to higher authority, 1800 (Box 48, Folder 1185)
  - Appointment of Manuel de Flor, governor, by José Paredes of Royal Justice, 1800 (Box 48, Folder 1186)
  - Receipt of flour from Sebastián Peréz, 1800 (Box 48, Folder 1187)
  - Decree by Juan Pedo Yuxamin, subdelegate, concerning elections of Amozoque, 1800 (Box 48, Folder 1188)
  - List of debts of masters of the guild, 1801 (Box 48, Folder 1189)
  - Testimony concerning sale of the meat supply, 1801 (Box 48, Folder 1190)
  - Huexotzingo. Election of governor, mayor and other authorities of the Indians, 1801 (Box 48, Folder 1191)
  - Election of governor, mayor, and other authorities by the Indians, San Juan de los Llanos, 1801 (Box 48, Folder 1192)
  - Election of governor, mayor, and other authorities by the Indians, Teciutlan, 1801 (Box 48, Folder 1193)
  - Election of governor, mayor, and other authorities by the Indians, Tetela, 1801 (Box 48, Folder 1194)
  - Xochimilco. Election of governor, mayor, and other authorities by the Indians, 1801 (Box 48, Folder 1195)
  - Certificates of the 1801 elections of the Indians, 1801 - 1802 (Box 48, Folder 1196)
  - Texepi. Election of governor, mayor, and other authorities by the Indians, 1801 - 1802 (Box 48, Folder 1197)
  - Subdelegate, José Ignacio Carnicero, revenue given to the Chautla government, 1802 (Box 48, Folder 1198)
  - Receipt form Santiago Carreto, 1802 (Box 48, Folder 1199)
  - Decree by the governor concerning Estates, 1802 (Box 48, Folder 1200)
  - Decree concerning defendants in prison, 1802 (Box 48, Folder 1201)
  - Petition by citizens and officials of Puebla concerning government, 1802 (Box 48, Folder 1202)
  - Decree concerning establishment of a school, Totomehuacan, 1802 (Box 48, Folder 1203)
  - Receipts from Miguél Mayol López y Herrera, of payment from the chaplaincy founded by Pedro del Rio Jiménez, 1802 - 1820 (Box 48, Folder 1204)
  - Petition by Santiago Peréz to marry María Joséfa Gertrúdis Pena, 1803 (Box 48, Folder 1205)
  - Tomás del Villar, declaration of rents earned, 1803 (Box 48, Folder 1206)
  - Receipt of flour from the Viceroy, 1803 (Box 48, Folder 1207)
  - Concerning extraction from the power of Ignacio Carrasquero of grains gathered in Chalcatongo, 1804 (Box 48, Folder 1208)
  - Two certificates of health, 1804 (Box 48, Folder 1209)
  - Action concerning the meeting of charity for the education of children, 1804 (Box 48, Folder 1210)
  - List of officials of towns in Puebla Bishopric, 1804 (Box 48, Folder 1211)
  - Citizens of Zacatlán de las Manzanas vs. the tithe collector, Manuel Peréz del Castillo, 1804 (Box 48, Folder 1212)
  - Certificate of revenue received by the Royal Storehouse, 1806 (Box 48, Folder 1213)
  - Yzucar. Election of governor, mayor and other authorities of the Indians, 1806 (Box 48, Folder 1214)
  - Receipt by Franciso Zomacona of paper from José Martínez, 1807 (Box 48, Folder 1215)
  - Manuel Gutiérrez del Solar, receipt from Miguél Mollol, 1808 (Box 48, Folder 1216)
  - Meeting concerning the office of mayor (Mayor del Partido) of San Juan del los Llanos, 1808 (Box 48, Folder 1217)
  - Bill of expenses of the citizens of San Nicolás Tierra Nueva in a pursuit ordered through the councilman, Agustín del Rivero, 1808 (Box 48, Folder 1218)
  - Decree by José Yrrigaray, governor, concerning the parish of Tepeylualco, 1808 (Box 48, Folder 1219)
  - Decree by the Count of la Cadena concerning taxation of aguardiente, 1809 (Box 49, Folder 1220)
  - Citizens of San Juan Bautista de Ahuacatlán vs. Antonio Ignacio Mendéz, presbyter, and José María Sánchez, school teacher, concerning the elections of authorities of the Indians, 1809 (Box 49, Folder 1221)
  - San Luis. Elections of officials of the Indians, 1809 (Box 49, Folder 1222)
  - Pedro de Larrea, record of rents for the lottery, 1811 (Box 49, Folder 1223)
  - Petition by the citizens of Santa María Chicmetatitlán concerning a three-day religious festival, 1811 (Box 49, Folder 1224)
  - Petition concerning the marriage of Joaquín Zeleta y Rivadencira and María Dolores Bedoy y Bernal, 1811 (Box 49, Folder 1225)
  - Receipts signed B. Larrantaga, 1812, 1813 (Box 49, Folder 1226)
  - List of debts of José Antonio Mota, 1813 (Box 49, Folder 1227)
  - Oath of loyalty to the king, 1813 (Box 49, Folder 1228)
  - Decrees concerning General Courts, 1813 - 1820 (Box 49, Folder 1229)
  - Financial report of Puebla to the capital (fragment), 1815 (Box 49, Folder 1230)
  - Five certificates by the priests of Atlixco, Juxtepeq, San Andrés, Chalchicomula, and Huiziheque and the justice of the War Department, 1817 (Box 49, Folder 1231)
  - A report on the people of Puebla, 1817 (Box 49, Folder 1232)
  - Complaints of the Indians of Sta. María Tetela against the subdelegate Francisco González, 1817 (Box 49, Folder 1233)
  - Transfer of power to Commander Francisco Yanez from the Puebla authorities, 1817 (Box 49, Folder 1234)
  - Petition by Lieutenant José de Amor concerning the Indians of Tecontepec, 1819 (Box 49, Folder 1235)
  - Correspondence concerning religious and parochial matters, 1819 (Box 49, Folder 1236)
  - José Mariano Peréz de Saltazar receipt from Miguél Mallol, 1819 (Box 49, Folder 1237)
  - Petition by José Volante y Ocariz concerning the Indians of Tehuacan, 1829 (Box 49, Folder 1238)
  - Record of the lands of the Royal House of Sr. San Antonio Abad, 1820 (Box 49, Folder 1239)
  - Report of replacement of the late governor by Juan Ignacio, 1820 (Box 49, Folder 1240)
  - Termination of dealings between Fernando Taboada and the mill of Sta. Domingo, 1821 (Box 49, Folder 1241)
  - Decrees concerning governance, 1822 (Box 49, Folder 1242)
  - Deed of a house, Portal de las Flores, 1822 - 1824 (Box 49, Folder 1243)
  - Rough drafts of letters of José María Crespo y Mongardin, attorney, 1823 (Box 49, Folder 1244)
  - Receipt from Luis Agassis for construction of his house Nigil, 1825 (Box 49, Folder 1245)
  - List of debts owed by individuals, 1825 (Box 49, Folder 1246)
  - Case concerning salaries of scribes and attorneys, 1825 - 1827 (Box 49, Folder 1247)
  - Visit to defendants in prison, 1826 (Box 49, Folder 1248)
  - Decree concerning lottery of Manuel Oropeza, 1828 (Box 49, Folder 1249)
  - Citizens of Sta. Isabel Tepetsala concerning their town, 1828 (Box 49, Folder 1250)
  - Sale of a house of a chaplaincy, 1828 (Box 49, Folder 1251)
  - Report to the governor of the inspection of the militia, 1832 (Box 49, Folder 1252)
  - Criminal Justices visit to the prison of Puebla, 1835 (Box 49, Folder 1253)
  - Appointment of Gregorio Sandovál as criminal judge, 1835 (Box 49, Folder 1254)
  - Accounts of government pensions, 1835 - 1839 (Box 49, Folder 1255)
  - Marriage license, signed by the Bishop of Durango, 1836 (Box 49, Folder 1256)
  - Provision of the courts of Tlapa and Zacapoatla, 1837 (Box 49, Folder 1257)
  - Provincial rent administration concerning forty-seven arrobas of wax without proper customs documents, 1837 (Box 49, Folder 1258)
  - Account book, presented by José Rafael Larrasilla to the court, 1839 (Box 49, Folder 1259)
  - Report by a scribe concerning a house, 1839 (Box 49, Folder 1260)
  - Notice of powers and decrees concerning agents, attorneys, 1831 - 1852 (Box 49, Folder 1261)
  - Letters to José María Carreto, attorney of Puebla, concerning private and business matters from Manuel Díaz, 1839 Jun 9, Juan Manuel de Madora, 1843 Aug 21, Sep 19, Micaela González, 1860 Feb 17, 1839, 1843, 1860 (Box 49, Folder 1262)
  - Appointment of the 2nd tribunal commissary, 1842 (Box 49, Folder 1263)
  - Correspondence concerning salaries of the judges, 1842 (Box 49, Folder 1264)
  - Report by Francisco Guevara, scribe, concerning the carrying out of his office, 1842 (Box 49, Folder 1265)
  - Recommendations made to the justices concerning matters of judicial proceedings, 1842 - 1845 (Box 49, Folder 1266)
  - Rough draft concerning matters of the Real Hacienda (incomplete), Circa 1843 (Box 50, Folder 1267)
  - Batallon de Independencia roster roll, including expenses of the company, 1846 (Box 50, Folder 1268)
  - Letter sent to Gregorio Sandovál by Manuel Abad for the governor acknowledging his donation to the treasury of Puebla, 1846 (Box 50, Folder 1269)
  - Minutes of a meeting of the Congress of Puebla sent to Gregorio Sandovál, 1846 (Box 50, Folder 1270)
  - Appointments of 1st judge, of Matamoros, 1847 (Box 50, Folder 1271)
  - Official communications sent to Gregorio Sandovál informing him of convocations of the Congress of Puebla, 1847 (Box 50, Folder 1272)
  - Official communication sent to Gregorio Sandovál asking him to accomplish his duties of the Congress, considering the difficult political condition of the country, 1847 (Box 50, Folder 1273)
  - Part of the records of the Administration of Tobacco, of S. Juan de los Llanos, 1848 (Box 50, Folder 1274)
  - Official communications to Gregorio Sandovál concerning political affairs in Puebla after North American invasion, 1848 (Box 50, Folder 1275)
  - Concerning war with U.S. (fragment), Circa 1848 (Box 50, Folder 1276)
  - Petition to the state government concerning authorization of the town council of Cholula, 1848 -1849 (Box 50, Folder 1277)
  - Certificate recognizing the burial of José Fernández Aguilar, 1853 (Box 50, Folder 1278)
  - Appointment of Gregorio Sandovál to a council of Puebla, 1855 (Box 50, Folder 1279)
  - Records of Nicolás Seoane, 1856 (Box 50, Folder 1280)
  - Action concerning the scribes available in the capital, 1858 (Box 50, Folder 1281)
  - Books 1 and 2 of the records of lands of the Convent of Sta. María de los Angeles, 1860 (Box 50, Folder 1282)
  - Petition by J. de la Mora to the prefect of Guadalajara asking for 15 soldiers to escort prisoners, 1865 (Box 50, Folder 1283)
  - Debts owed by Ignacio Romero Vargas to Gregorio Sandovál scribe, 1873 (Box 50, Folder 1284)
  - Notarized incorporation of a company, "Shormann and Header", 1901 (Box 50, Folder 1285)
  - Petition by Bartolomé Martínez, ex-governor of Sta. Ines de Aguatempa against the subdelegate, undated (Box 50, Folder 1286)
  - Petition to the vicar by Juan Ignacio Uzubie Pacheco concerning Rosalia Galbadon's marriage, undated (Box 50, Folder 1287)
  - Unidentified fragments, undated (Box 50, Folder 1288)